if you're thinking about moving to the
Austin Texas area I encourage you to
watch this video first as someone who
has relocated myself as well as assisted
hundreds of families in relocating to
the central Texas area I know firsthand
that Austin Texas as amazing as it is
isn't your only option that there are
some amazing and even more affordable
suburbs that you might not even know
about hi I'm Andrea dck realtor and ass
IA burer with V real estate and today
we'll be taking a deep dive into Austin
as well as a comparison of some of the
other um wonderful areas where I'm at
just north in Temple
Belton okay it's no surprise that Texas
itself has become a relocation hotspot
um we have a booming job market we have
a relatively low cost of living a high
quality of life and just people from
across the country are drawn here Texas
has no state income tax which is a huge
draw now one of the things that people
are always aware of is that while we
don't have a state income tax our
property taxes are slightly higher but
overall lower cost of living When
comparing Austin to more North so where
I am I'm in the Temple belon area which
is an hour north of Austin Texas we're
right on the I35 Corridor so it's a
super easy route and access to get here
sometimes traffic is a little heavier
going down to Austin but to be expected
now in Austin you have a higher cost of
living with a median home price of
around
$450 as of December of 2024 and then
Temple belon um you have a more
affordable median house price of about
273,000 I'd say a lot of my firsttime
home buyers can expect to find a
wonderful home in the
260 to 310 price point as of right now
so that's nearly half the cost of Austin
Texas now weather uh Texas weather is
wild um I moved here about 10 years ago
from Las Vegas Nevada and so I thought
you know comparable heat it's going to
be fine it is not a comparable heat
Vegas is a dry heat whereas Texas is
more of a humid heat but it's sunny a
lot um the weather does tend to
fluctuate very
rapidly last week for example so we're
in February last week it was freezing we
had freeze warnings and today we are
actually hitting the80s so that's that's
pretty Wild Winters in Texas are mild
with highs being in the 6 60s and lows
in the 40s and then summers are long and
hot with temperatures frequently hitting
triple digits uh from May through
September and a lot of sunny
days Austin Texas actually averages 60%
Sunshine annually if you love sunshine
you can't go wrong with Texas in Texas
in general Texans are known for their
Hospitality this is kind of a funny
story at least to me when I first moved
here my my husband is from Texas the
hospitality actually threw me off of it
I can recall driving down the street one
day to our new home and there were these
people walking the street and they were
just waving to him and I said do you
know them and he said no they're just
waving they like oh people just wave to
each other when they're driving or when
they're walking they just wave all the
time you drive past each other on the
street they wave that's a big one one of
my biggest draws to Texas is I wanted to
be immersed in a Kinder culture and man
did I get it I mean Texans want to visit
they want to see how you're doing and
they really care about their Community
which is really great if you're in the
grocery store someone might stop you in
line in the at checkout for 10 minutes
just to talk about you know your kids or
where you're from or how they love your
outfit so just tack on a little bit of
extra time when you're going anywhere
you are probably not going to be rushed
another moment was we were in a
restaurant waiting to be seated and this
really sweet older gentleman sat next to
my husband and they would in this really
big long conversation about just family
or something and when the gentleman left
and he was called to to his feed I asked
my husband I said how did you know him
and he said I didn't know him I was just
visiting with him and it took me quite a
bit of time to get used to people just
being very kind and engaged with each
other so something now that I absolutely
love but it was a bit of a shock and
people do say yes ma'am no ma'am
whenever I would go home to Vegas people
would say don't call me ma'am I'm old
I'm not you're making me feel old and in
Texas it's just a form of respect and so
no matter the age yes ma'am no ma'am is
just the equivalent of yes and no and uh
that that's really interesting the very
Southern ways that are still very
prominent here so what is it like living
in Austin Texas so Austin is ranked
number nine in the US new's best places
to
live and it is a metro area with over 2
million residents so there are a lot of
people there um you know originally when
I moved here I thought I want to be near
the city but not exactly in it I wanted
to have access to amenities but not be
right in the city just you know same to
being in Vegas um but Austin is a huge
Tech Hub it's referred to silicone Hills
it has big companies like Tesla Dell
Apple Google having a very strong
presence in the area so the job market
in Austin is very robust and
particularly in technology Education and
healthc Care now especially when Co
happened I found where I am in in Temple
Belton that a lot of people were
relocating from Austin because it was
more affordable
because they could have a $500,000
budget and get a much smaller house with
a smaller lot in Austin Drive 45 minutes
an hour north and get a much larger home
um maybe on a bigger sized lot with a
bigger backyard with a little more
privacy and especially when a lot of
people were working from home this
wasn't a big deal for a lot of people or
people for example who were only
traveling to Austin for short periods of
time you know having come from Vegas
driving 45 minutes in traffic uh is kind
of a norm and so 45 minutes 10 hour of
no traffic listening to podcasts or just
um enjoying your drive that's worth it
to a lot of people lifestyle
entertainment so of course Austin is
famous for its motto Keep Austin Weird I
can recall getting off the plane for the
first time and the airport even felt
very just um unique and cultured and
diverse and there was just a lot going
on and I loved it I thought it was so
cool a lot of people want to be immersed
in the center at that um so there are so
many cool things to do in Austin you
have ladybird Lake where you can uh
kayak or paddle board there's 351 acres
in Zilker Park um there's just no
shortage of outdoor fun other
attractions you have Barton Springs Pool
Zilker Botanical Garden mckin fall State
Park and then of course there's
nightlife and festivals you have down
downtown Austin six street with um bars
and dining and just nightlife hug and
live music and then you have South
Congress which is trendy for shopping
dining iconic murals uh the iconic mural
I love you so much we also have Austin
City Limits and South by Southwest which
are two world famous festivals putting
Austin's music seen on the map with a
median household income of
98,000 Austin does have diverse housing
options according to Texas schools.gov
in 2021 to
2022 Austin ISD had a total of
123 schools 71,000 is enrolled and an
overall B rating 88 out of 100 with 13.8
students per teacher so a lot of school
options now let's talk about about the
temple bton area a little bit more I
like I said I had thought I wanted to be
in Austin I rented for a little bit in
George Town which is about 25 30 minutes
north of Austin and then that grew very
quickly georget toown is so cool it grew
very quickly and then my husband is
actually from the Temple belon area so
we did end up here never would have
thought growing up that I'd be from
Temple or belon Texas but here I am I
love it I wouldn't have it any other way
now what's going on here in Temple
Belton and the reason I say Temple
Belton is there is a lot of overlap
between the two if you are trying to
decide where to live in which um you can
be in Temple and still be within belon
ISD you can be in Temple and part of
Temple ISD I think a lot of it boils
down to when you're here
geographically where do you want to be
do you want to be closer to the the
hospitals um we are actually one of the
largest medical hubs in the area we the
largest between Austin and Dallas you
know do you want to be closer to there
do you want to be closer to umhb do you
want to be closer to the VA hospital we
get a lot of military who are moving to
be close to Fort
Cavazos um which is in colen that's
about anywhere from 25 to 40 minutes in
belon there we have um Wilson art we
have space X in McGregor which is just
20 minutes north we are 40 minutes south
of Waco Texas so again a lot of people
will come from there you know the closer
that you get to Austin being right on
I35 gets great access and ease whether
going to Austin south to Austin North to
wakeo if you're going west to Fort
Cavazos colen
area really easy access and honestly
very minimal traffic sometimes if I'm
leaving for example to go to the Austin
Airport I'll give myself a little grace
period because it can get congested near
Austin but really along that I35
Corridor I really don't hit much traffic
and you don't really don't experience
much that there so Temple's cost of
living is 4% below the state average
with a median home price of 26 69,000
was the uh median home price in Temple
and 309 was the median in belon and so
when we're comparing school districts um
I will say that I do feel that belon ISD
is slightly more sought after than
Temple ISD and so we can kind of find
that in in either Temple or belon and
belon ISD has a total of 17 schools with
13,298 total enrollment total ranking
being a b 87 out of 100 just right
around where Austin is and 4.2 students
per teacher and then Temple has Temple
ISD has a total of
8,395 total student enrollment with an
overall Ste rating 77 out of 100 with 14
students per teacher and again this is
according to Texas
schools.gov and then now Bell County in
general um Temple and belon are both
part of Bell County and then you can
expand out a bit to you know um Colleen
fer Heights um and then you have Troy
Little River Academy C these are all
some really really great options if
you're looking to be within Bell County
uh overall Bell County has a total
population of 370,000 according to the
US Census Bureau and median household in
income of
70,000 all of which is kind of just
highlighting that it's a it's more
affordable to live here as you get
closer to Austin that price per square
foot and that average home price does
seem to go up but it's a trade-off for
being more immersing to the city
lifestyle now if you are looking for new
construction in belon ISD there are so
many options since it is growing so
quickly here some hot new communities
that I have been showing and selling and
often will be Mesa Ridge um which is
right off of 317 which is a main street
through thorough through um belon um
Mesa Ridge there are quite a few
builders in there Flint Rock
Omega Jerry Wright kurs just to name a
few Three Creeks Three Creeks is really
awesome it is on the way to it it's
technically belt an ISD it's off of i14
headed out to the Harker Heights Colleen
area so we do get a lot and I feel an
equal mix of people from working at the
hospitals in belon cuz it's about a
20-minute drive as well as people who
are now working at Fork of oos which is
about a 24 minute drive um there are
walking trails in Three Creeks there
it's just very close to still house
Hollow Lake close to shopping um lots of
builders in that Community you have
more luxury Builders like KS you have
more affordable homes like deer Horton
um again stylecraft Omega and then
there's a lot of resales that Community
has been there for a long time so there
are quite a few options to purchase a
resale home or a new construction home
in this market a lot of those Builders
are offering insane vain incentives to
purchase a new construction home to
offload some of that
inventory um I've been getting clients
you know all their closing costs paid
for um interest insanely low interest
rates buying you know Builders are
buying down the rates they're offering
concessions towards those uh appliance
packages throwing in blinds I mean
there's a lot of really great options so
you have Three Creeks out that way uh of
Westwood is doing some new phases in
belon groves at Lakewood Ranch we have
east and west and then in Temple uh
partrick Ranch Hillside Village South
Point just to name a
few and then um as far as outdoor
activities there are so many outdoor
activities uh you have still house
Hollow Dam and then you have belon Lake
tons of opportunity for fishing boating
kaying if you love outdoor activities
and you want to still be immersed in
nature you might want to consider
Morgan's Point Resort as a place to live
I I just recently did a video your guide
To Living in Morgan Point Texas that
kind of highlights this area and you can
get some lakefront properties you can be
very close to living on the lake um
where deer roome your proper property
really need and never far from uh you're
just never really far from outdoor
activities and dining we have plenty of
grocery stores here multiple Walmarts
multiple HS Target Best Buy Olive
Garden Downtown Temple and downtown
belon are booming right now with new
restaurants and amenities and I'm going
to be doing a tour pretty soon here of C
Texas too is 20 minutes north of Temple
bon in between Temple Bon and Austin it
is a Hidden Gem I absolutely love it
it's a golf course Community people
drive around on their on their golf
carts um they call it the the upand
cominging Fredericksburg which if you
are familiar with Fredericksburg it's
sort of wine country and it just has its
own unique feel you again you're you're
still about 20 25 minutes out from
bigger amenities with getting that very
small town field the the the biggest
this is so silly one of the biggest
complaints I've heard is that you can't
get a lot of like door Dash and um home
grocery deliveries which for really busy
families that's a really big deal so
just a a little thing but I'll do a
video on that one coming up soon so
you're considering moving to Austin
Texas and are open to maybe some of the
surrounding areas now what um here are
some tips to help you narrow down where
to live write down your musthaves and
non-negotiables whether that's location
price School District size of home um
maybe being immersed in the city or
being out in the country with trees that
is really going to and actually pretty
easily help us kind of understand where
you need to be do you prefer um city
life or small downtown charm and then
set your budget knowing your budget will
really help us determine where we need
to um kind of look at things for you and
then call me let's discuss your goals
and create a plan I'm here to guide you
every step of the way so whether you're
drawn to the vibrant culture of Austin
Texas or the smalltown charm of Temple
belon Central Texas has something for
everyone you can book a call with me
below I'd love to discuss your next
steps and until next time I'm Andrea
dudic realtor and Associate broker with
v RealD